Register of the Eric Voegelin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1921-1987
  - "Le régime administratif: Avantages et inconvénients" (with Adolf Merkl), Mémoires de l'Académie internationale de droit comparé, 1935 (Box-folder 54: 26)
  - Review of F. Sander, Verfassungsurkunde, 1935 (Box-folder 54: 27)
    Holograph and galley proofs
  - Review of Godehard Jos. Ebers, Verfassungsrecht, Zentralblatt für die juristische Praxis, 1935 (Box-folder 54: 28)
  - Translations of miscellaneous legal documents, 1935 (Box-folder 54: 29)
    Research material, notes, holograph, typescript, and correspondence
  - Speech relating to fascism, 1935 November 12 (Box-folder 54: 30)
    Notes and outline
  - "Die Neuordnung des österreichischen Staatswesens ...", circa 1936 (Box-folder 54: 31)
    Holograph, and typewritten French translation. Includes outline of untitled speech at some unidentified Volksbildungshaus, 30 March 1936
  - Review of H. Raschhofer, Der politische Volksbegriff im modernen Italien, circa 1936 (Box-folder 54: 32)
  - Der autoritäre Staat, 1936
    - Notes (Box-folder 54: 33)
    - Holograph (in part typescript)
      - I (Box-folder 55: 1)
      - II (Box-folder 55: 2)
      - III (Box-folder 55: 3)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box-folder 55: 4)
      - Letter, dated 29 October 1935, by an unidentified high government official to the President of Austria, relating to several points of constitutional order raised by Eric Voegelin in the book (Box-folder 55: 5)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 55: 6)
  - Reviews of Richard Schmitz, Die berufsständische Neuordnung in Osterreich, and of Odo Neustädter-Stürmer, Die berufsständische Gesetzgebung in Osterreich, 1936 (Box-folder 55: 7)
  - "Die philosophische Anthropologie als Grundwissenschaft,", 1936 April 30 (Box-folder 55: 8)
    Speech, Akademischer Verein für medizinische Psychologie, Vienna, Austria. Outline
  - "Die Führer Asiens gegen Europa,", 1936 May 26 (Box-folder 55: 9)
    Speech, Volksbildungshauses Grazer Urania, Graz, Austria. Notes and outline
  - "Die Voraussetzungen der westeuropäischen Demokratie,", 1936 May 27 (Box-folder 55: 10)
    Speech, Volksbildungshauses Grazer Urania, Graz, Austria. Outline and notes
  - "Volksbildung, Wissenschaft und Politik," Monatschrift für Kultur und Politik, 1936 July (Box-folder 55: 11)
    Notes, outline, holograph, typescript, and printed copy
  - Translation of Austrian Supreme Court decision 1 Ob 616/36, 1936 August (Box-folder 55: 12)
    Holograph, typescript, and letter from Assen Hartenau
  - Translation of review by Gustav Walker of Arpad Plesch and Martin Domke, Die österreichische Völkerbundanleihe 1923/1943, 1936 October 6 (Box-folder 55: 13)
    Holograph, typescript, and correspondence
  - "Sein und Sollen,", 1936 October 7 (Box-folder 55: 14)
  - "Gutachten über die Spezialitätenordnung von 1925,", 1936 October 27 (Box-folder 55: 15)
    Notes, holograph, and correspondence
  - "Joseph Redlich," Juristische Blätter, 1936 December 12 (Box-folder 55: 16)
    Notes, holograph, typescript, galley proofs, and printed copy
  - Review of Alois Hudal, Die Grundlagen des Nationalsozialismus, circa 1937 (Box-folder 55: 17)
  - Review of Eduard Baumgarten, Benjamin Franklin: Der Lehrmeister der amerikanischen Revolution, Zeitschrift für öffentliches Recht, 1937 (Box-folder 55: 18)
    Notes, holograph, typescript, and galley proofs
  - Review of Hans Krupa, Carl Schmitts Theorie des Politischen, Zeitschrift für öffentliches Recht, 1937 (Box-folder 55: 19)
  - "Das Timurbild der Humanisten," Zeitschrift für öffentliches Recht, 1937 (Box-folder 55: 20)
  - "Die Psychologie der sozialen Mythenbildung,", 1937 January 21 (Box-folder 55: 21)
    Speech, Akademischer Verein für Medizinische Psychologie, Vienna, Austria. Announcement
  - "The Change in the Ideas on Government and Constitution in Austria since 1918,", 1937 April (Box-folder 55: 22)
    Third of three memoranda submitted to the International Studies Conference on Peaceful Change, Tenth session, Paris, France, 28 June-3 July 1937. Research material, typescript, and mimeographed copy. Includes memoranda of Otto Brunner and Gregor Sebba
  - "Meinungsäusserung und Meinungsbildung," Neue freie Presse, 1937 May 30 (Box-folder 55: 23)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy
  - "Osterreich und die Studienkonferenz," Neue freie Presse, 1937 June 19 (Box-folder 55: 24)
  - "Was dürfen die Menschen wissen?" Neue freie Presse, 1937 November 7 (Box-folder 55: 25)
  - "Was wissen die Menschen von sichselber?", 1937 November 8 (Box-folder 55: 26)
    Speech, Psychologischer Institut der Universität zu Wien, Vienna, Austria. Outline
  - "Gesellschaftslehre und Staatsrecht,", 1937 November 19 (Box-folder 55: 27)
    Speech, Volkstümliche Universitäts-Vorträge, Vienna, Austria. Research material and correspondence
  - "Der neue Stil des Krieges," Neue freie Presse, 1937 November 20 (Box-folder 55: 28)
  - "Flucht in die Arbeit," Neue freie Presse, 1937 December 16 (Box-folder 55: 29)
  - Review of J. Boissonnet, La misère par la surabondance: Karl Marx, père de la crise mondiale, American Economic Review, circa 1938 (Box-folder 55: 30)
    Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence
  - Die politischen Religionen, 1938
    - Notes (Box-folder 55: 31)
    - Holograph (Box-folder 55: 32)
    - Typescript of foreword (Box-folder 55: 33)
      Includes holograph
    - Review (Box-folder 55: 34)
  - "Gemeinschaft und Kampf,", 1938 January 11 (Box-folder 55: 35)
  - "Kampf und Erkenntnis der politischen Begriffslage der Gegenwart,", 1938 February 11 (Box-folder 55: 36)
    Speech, Linz, Austria. Outline
  - Translation of Paul Valéry, "Sémiramis,", 1938 Spring (Box-folder 55: 37)
  - "Memorandum on the Teaching of International Relations,", 1938 March (Box-folder 55: 38)
    Submitted to the International Studies Conference, Eleventh Session, Prague, Czechoslovakia, 23-27 May 1938. Mimeographed copy
  - "Totalitarian Climate,", circa 1939 (Box-folder 55: 39)
  - Review of Gaetano Mosca, The Ruling Class, The Journal of Politics, 1939 (Box-folder 56: 1)
    Typescript and correspondence
  - "The Plight and Problem of Refugees,", 1939 January (Box-folder 56: 2)
    Speech, The Community Church of Boston, Massachusetts. Outline
  - "Political Religions,", 1939 March 13 (Box-folder 56: 3)
    Speech, Bennington College, Vermont (also given at William Y. Elliott's seminar at Harvard University, 22 March 1939). Outline
  - "Democracy and the Individual,", 1939 July 7 (Box-folder 56: 4)
    Radio talk, NBC-WMAQ, Evanston, Illinois. Typescript and correspondence with Arthur N. Holcombe, Ernest H. Hahne, J. J. Pierri, Harry Harrison, Robert J. Doyle, A. Moran, Vital Speeches
  - "Modern Politics and the Decay of Christianity,", 1939 August 1 (Box-folder 56: 5)
    Speech, Northwestern University, Chicago, Illinois. Outline
  - "History of Political Ideas,", 1939-1950
    See also CORRESPONDENCE, Macmillan Company
    - Notes (Box-folder 56: 6-7)
    - Outline (Box-folder 56: 8)
    - Holograph (Box-folder 56: 9-12)
    - Holograph (Box-folder 57: 1-3)
    - Typescript
      - Photocopy of carbon copy (Box-folder 57: 4-7)
      - Photocopy of carbon copy (Box-folder 58: 1-7)
      - Photocopy of carbon copy (Box-folder 59: 1-8)
      - Photocopy of carbon copy (Box-folder 60: 1-3)
      - Original fragments (Box-folder 60: 4-12)
        Includes holograph fragments
  - "Extended Strategy: A New Technique of Dynamic Relations," The Journal of Politics, 1940 (Box-folder 61: 1)
    Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Robert J. Harris, Jr.
  - "The Growth of the Race Idea," The Review of Politics, 1940 July (Box-folder 61: 2)
  - "The Technique of National Socialist Conquest,", 1940 October 30 (Box-folder 61: 3)
    Speech, Rotary Club, Birmingham, Alabama. Outline and correspondence
  - "The Mongol Orders of Submission to European Powers, 1245-1255," Byzantion, 1940-1941
    - Notes and research material (Box-folder 61: 4)
    - German manuscript, circa 1938 (Box-folder 61: 5)
      Entitled "Die Staatsbriefe der Mongolenkhane." Typescript (in part holograph) and correspondence with Springer-Verlag
    - English manuscript, circa 1939 (Box-folder 61: 6)
      Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with R. P. Blake
    - French and Latin fragments, undated (Box-folder 61: 7)
  - Review of Maxine Y. Sweezy, The Structure of the Nazi Economy, circa 1941 (Box-folder 61: 8)
  - Review of James Brown Scott, The Law, The State, and the International Community, The Review of Politics, 1941 (Box-folder 61: 9)
    Holograph, typescript, and letter from Waldemar Gurian
  - "Some Problems of German Hegemony," The Journal of Politics, 1941 May (Box-folder 61: 10)
    Typescript (annotated by Heinrich Brüning), printed copy, and correspondence with Heinrich Brüning
  - "Two Recent Contributions to the Science of Law," Review of Politics, 1941 July (Box-folder 61: 11)
    Review of N. S. Timasheff, Introduction to the Sociology of Law, and of E. Bodenheimer, Jurisprudence: The Philosophy and Method of the Law. Holograph, typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Waldemar Gurian
  - Review of Ernst Fraenkel, The Dual State: A Contribution to the Theory of Dictatorship, The Journal of Politics, 1942 (Box-folder 61: 12)
  - Review of Huntington Cairns, The Theory of Legal Science, Louisiana Law Review, 1942 (Box-folder 61: 13)
    Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Jefferson B. Fordham. Includes a comment by Huntington Cairns on Eric Voegelin's review
  - "British War Aims,", 1942 February 21 (Box-folder 61: 14)
    Speech, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana. Research material, outline, typescript, and clipping
  - "Nietzsche and Pascal,", circa 1943
    - Notes (Box-folder 61: 15)
    - Holograph and typescript (Box-folder 61: 16)
  - Review of Marvin Farber, The Foundation of Phenomenology: Edmund Husserl and the Quest for a Rigorous Science of Philosophy, 1943 (Box-folder 61: 17)
    Holograph, typescript, and correspondence with Leo Strauss and Marvin Farber
  - "Studien zur Theorie des Bewusstseins,", 1943 (Box-folder 62: 1)
  - Review of Alec de Montmorency, The Enigma of Admiral Darlan, circa 1943 June (Box-folder 62: 2)
  - Review of John H. Hallowell, The Decline of Liberalism as an Ideology, with Particular References to German Political Thought, The Journal of Politics, 1944 (Box-folder 62: 3)
    Holograph, typescript, and correspondence with Robert S. Rankin
  - "Nietzsche, the Crisis and the War," The Journal of Politics, 1944 May (Box-folder 62: 4)
  - "Siger de Brabant," Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, 1944 June (Box-folder 62: 5)
    Typescript, printed copy, and letter to Waldemar Gurian
  - "Political Theory and the Pattern of General History," The American Political Science Review, 1944 August (Box-folder 62: 6)
    Contribution, Research in Political Theory: A Symposium (a meeting of the Political Theory Panel of the Research Committee of the American Political Science Association), Washington, D.C., 20-21 November 1943. Typewritten summary of the principal issues discussed at the meeting, and printed copy of the final report
  - Review of Albert R. Chandler, Rosenberg's Nazi Myth, circa 1945 (Box-folder 62: 7)
    Typescript, galley proofs, and correspondence
  - Review of Hans Kelsen, General Theory of Law and State and of William Ebenstein, The Pure Theory of Law, circa 1945 (Box-folder 62: 8)
  - Review of Carlo Sforza, Contemporary Italy: Its Intellectual and Moral Origins, The Journal of Politics, 1945 (Box-folder 62: 9)
  - "Sorel, Georges,", 1945 (Box-folder 62: 10)
    Notes and typescript of entry for Encyclopedia Britannica. Includes correspondence with the editor
  - Review of Friedrich Engel-Janosi, The Growth of German Historicism, circa 1945 May (Box-folder 62: 11)
    Typescript and correspondence with Robert S. Rankin
  - Review of Frederick L. Schuman, Soviet Politics: At Home and Abroad, The Journal of Politics, 1946 (Box-folder 62: 12)
  - "Zu Sanders 'Allgemeine Staatslehre,'" Osterreichische Zeitschrift für öffentliches Recht, 1946 (Box-folder 62: 13)
    Holograph, galley proofs, and printed copy
  - "Bakunin's Confession," The Journal of Politics, 1946 February (Box-folder 62: 14)
  - "The Cyclical Theory of History and Twentieth Century Disintegration,", 1946 November 8 (Box-folder 62: 15)
    Conference paper, Southern Political Science Association, Fifteenth Annual Meeting, Knoxville, Tennessee. Clipping
  - Remarks, Round Table: Beyond Relativism in Political Theory, American Political Science Association, Forty-second Annual Meeting, Cleveland, Ohio, 1946 December 28 (Box-folder 62: 16)
    Typescript and correspondence with Arnold Brecht and Francis G. Wilson
  - "Political Science and the Intellectuals,", circa 1946-1950 (Box-folder 62: 17)
    Conference paper. Typescript
  - "Clericalism,", circa 1947 (Box-folder 62: 18)
    Typescript and letter from Frederic A. Ogg
  - Review of F. S. C. Northrop, The Meeting of East and West: An Inquiry Concerning World Understanding, circa 1947 (Box-folder 62: 19)
    Typescript and letter to Leo Strauss
  - Review of Rudolf Schlesinger, Soviet Legal Theory: Its Social Background and Development, The Journal of Politics, 1947 (Box-folder 62: 20)
    Typescript and letter to V. O. Key
  - "Plato's Egyptian Myth," The Journal of Politics, 1947 August (Box-folder 62: 21)
  - Review of Alfred von Verdross-Drossberg, Grundlinien der Antiken Rechts- und Staatsphilosophie, circa 1948 (Box-folder 62: 22)
  - Review of Julius Curtius, Sechs Jahre Minister der deutschen Republik and Bemühung um Osterreich: Das Scheitern des Zollunionsplans von 1931, circa 1948 (Box-folder 62: 23)
  - Review of Jan Huizinga, Homo Ludens, The Journal of Politics, 1948 (Box-folder 62: 24)
    Typescript and correspondence with V. O. Key
  - "The Western Revolutionary Movements,", 1948 March 12 (Box-folder 62: 25)
    Speech, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut. Correspondence with P. E. Corbett
  - "The Origins of Scientism," Social Research, 1948 December
    - Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Leo Strauss (Box-folder 62: 26)
    - German translation (Professor Pichl) entitled "Wissenschaft als Aberglaube: Die Ursprünge des Szientifismus," Wort und Wahrheit, 1951 May (Box-folder 62: 27)
  - Review of John Bowle, Western Political Thought: A Historical Introduction from the Origins to Rousseau, Review of Politics, 1949 (Box-folder 62: 28)
  - Review of Leo Strauss, On Tyranny: An Interpretation of Xenophon's Hiero, Review of Politics, 1949 (Box-folder 62: 29)
    Typescript of English and German versions
  - Speech, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, 1949 April (Box-folder 62: 30)
    Correspondence with Carl B. Swisher
  - "Goethe's Utopia," Radio talk, WLSU, Baton Rouge, Louisiana., 1949 April 29 (Box-folder 62: 31)
  - "The Philosophy of Existence: Plato's Gorgias," The Review of Politics, 1949 October (Box-folder 62: 32)
  - "The Church,", 1949 November 11 (Box-folder 62: 33)
    Conference paper, Southern Political Science Association, Eighteenth Annual Meeting, Knoxville, Tennessee. Typescript
  - "The Political Religions and their Implications for the Traditional American Doctrine,", 1949 December 29 (Box-folder 62: 34)
    Conference paper, American Political Science Association, Fifty-fourth Annual Meeting. Typescript
  - Review of Thomas G. Bergin and Max A. Fisch, translators, The New Science of Giambattista Vico, Catholic Historical Review, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 62: 35)
  - "Notes on T. S. Eliot's Four Quartets, ", circa 1950 (Box-folder 63: 1)
  - Review of Paul Koschaker, Europa und das römische Recht, circa 1950 (Box-folder 63: 2)
    Typescript and letter to Mr. Wilkerson
  - Impressions about his trip to Vienna, Austria, 1950 (Box-folder 63: 3)
    Notes
  - Series of two speeches (or courses), entitled "Das anthropologische Prinzip" and "Kreislauf und Fortschritt," Vienna, Austria, 1950 (Box-folder 63: 4)
    Notes and outlines
  - "Staat und Geschichte,", 1950 June 20-21 (Box-folder 63: 5)
    Speech, Rechts- und Staatswissenschaftliche Fakultät der Universität zu Wien, Vienna, Austria. Correspondence with Hans Schimm, Alfred von Verdross, Adolf Merkl, Ludwig von Adamovich. For unsuccessful invitation to Vienna in 1948, see CORRESPONDENCE, Gottfried Haberler and United States. Department of State
  - "The Formation of the Marxian Revolutionary Idea," The Review of Politics, 1950 July (Box-folder 63: 6)
  - "More's Utopia," Osterreichische Zeitschrift für öffentliches Recht, 1951 (Box-folder 63: 7)
  - "Machiavelli's Prince: Background and Formation," The Review of Politics, 1951 April (Box-folder 63: 8)
    Notes, typescript, and printed copy
  - "Gnostische Politik," Merkur, 1952 (Box-folder 63: 9)
    Typescript. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Merkur
  - The New Science of Politics: An Introduction, 1952
    See also COURSE MATERIAL, University of Notre Dame, Miscellany, 1961
    - Typescript (Box-folder 63: 10)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 63: 11)
    - Reviews
      - General (Box-folder 63: 12)
      - Kelsen, Hans, "A New Science of Politics" (Box-folder 63: 13)
      - "Journalism and Joachim's Children," Time, 1953 March 9 (Box-folder 63: 14)
        Printed copy and correspondence with Time and readers
    - German translation, (Ilse Gattenhof), 1959
      - Typescript
        - Preface (Box-folder 64: 1)
        - Index (Box-folder 64: 2)
      - Galley proofs of introduction (Box-folder 64: 3)
        See also CORRESPONDENCE, Verlag Styria
      - Correspondence (Box-folder 64: 4)
      - Reviews (Box-folder 64: 5)
    - Spanish translation of introduction (Emilio Sánchez Pintado), Atlantida, 1963 March-April (Box-folder 64: 6)
    - Italian translation, (Renato Pavetto), 1968 (Box-folder 64: 7)
      Review and correspondence with Renato Pavetto
  - "History of Ideas and Periods of Civilization,", 1952 February 21 (Box-folder 64: 8)
    Speech, Humanities Club, Washington, D.C. Correspondence with Friedrich Engel-Janosi
  - "Political Gnosis,", 1952 February 13 (Box-folder 64: 9)
    Talk at graduate seminar in political science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland. Correspondence with Thomas I. Cook
  - "The Discovery of the Soul--in Ancient and Modern Philosophy,", 1952 February 14 (Box-folder 64: 10)
    Speech, History of Ideas Club, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland. Typewritten abstract, and correspondence with Fritz Machlup and Bruce Wardropper
  - "The Wrath of Achilles" and "The Nature of Modernity,", 1952 February (Box-folder 64: 11)
    Speeches, St. John's College, Annapolis, Maryland. Correspondence with Jacob Klein
  - Notes, schedule, correspondence, and clippings relating to the five aforementioned engagements (Box-folder 64: 12)
  - "Political Science and the Intellectuals,", 1952 August 26 (Box-folder 64: 13)
    Conference paper, American Political Science Association, Buffalo, New York. Notes, typescript, and correspondence with Wesley L. Gould
  - Review of Fritz Wagner, Geschichtswissenschaft, American Political Science Review, 1953 (Box-folder 64: 14)
  - Review of Hannah Arendt, The Origins of Totalitarianism, The Review of Politics, 1953 January (Box-folder 64: 15)
  - "The Oxford Political Philosophers," The Philosophical Quarterly, 1953 April
    See also CORRESPONDENCE, Helmut Kuhn, Philosophical Quarterly, Philosophische Rundschau
    - Typescript and printed copy (Box-folder 64: 16)
    - German translation (Eric Voegelin) entitled "Philosophie der Politik in Oxford," Philosophische Rundschau, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 64: 17)
  - "The World of Homer," The Review of Politics, 1953 October (Box-folder 64: 18)
  - "Future of Communism,", 1953 December 2 (Box-folder 64: 19)
    Speech, Great Issues Course, University of Texas, Austin, Texas. Outline, clippings, and correspondence with Foy Clement and Tom K. Barton
  - Review of Ewart Lewis, Medieval Political Ideas, circa 1954 (Box-folder 64: 20)
  - Review of John Wild, Plato's Modern Enemies and the Theory of Natural Law, and of Ronald B. Levinson, In Defense of Plato, American Political Science Review, 1954 (Box-folder 64: 21)
    Typescript and letter to Emmette S. Redford
  - "What Is Political Theory?", 1954 November 5 (Box-folder 64: 22)
    Conference paper, Southern Political Science Association, Twenty-sixth Annual Meeting, University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina. Typescript. Includes critical response to Eric Voegelin's paper
  - Review of Raymond Polin, Politique et philosophie chez Thomas Hobbes, American Political Science Review, 1955 (Box-folder 64: 23)
  - "The Quest for Principles in Political Science,", 1955 April 14 (Box-folder 64: 24)
    Speech, Department of Political Science, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan. Notes, outlines, and correspondence with Frank Grace, Russell H. Fifield, James K. Pollock
  - "The Quest for Principles in Political Science,", 1955 April 22 (Box-folder 64: 25)
    Speech, Department of Political Science, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana. Correspondence with L. V. Howard. See speech of 14 April 1955 for outline
  - Series of papers, Conference on Democratic Theory, The Foundation for American Studies, Buck Hill Falls, Pennsylvania, 1955 June 22-30 (Box-folder 64: 26)
    Outline and correspondence with William S. Stokes
  - "The Historical Validity of Toynbee's Approach to Universal States,", 1955 November 19 (Box-folder 64: 27)
    Conference paper, Symposium, The Intent of Toynbee's History: A Cooperative Appraisal, Loyola University, Chicago, Illinois. Typescript and correspondence with Edward Gargan and Russell H. Fifield
  - Order and History, Vol.I: Israel and Revelation, 1956
    - Typescript
      - Introduction (Box-folder 65: 1)
        Includes correspondence with Robert Heilman, who annotated it
      - Part I (Box-folder 65: 2)
        Includes correspondence with Georg Jaffé
      - Part II (Box-folder 65: 3)
      - Part III (Box-folder 65: 4-5)
      - Part IV (Box-folder 65: 6)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 65: 7)
      See also Reviews
    - Reviews (Box-folder 65: 8)
    - German translation, typescript
      - Preface and introduction (Peter J. Opitz) (Box-folder 66: 1)
        Includes corrections by Eric Voegelin
      - Part I (Box-folder 66: 2)
      - Part II (Box-folder 66: 3)
      - Part III (Box-folder 66: 4)
      - Part IV (Box-folder 66: 5)
  - Debate, "Western Civilization: Rising or Falling?" Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1956 March (Box-folder 66: 6)
  - "Necessary Moral Bases for Communication in a Democracy,", 1956 March 21
    Speech, 75th Anniversary Conference, Marquette University, Milwaukee, Wisconsin
    - Outline and typescript (Box-folder 66: 7)
    - Correspondence with Robert A. Kidera, Reynolds C. Seitz, Edward A. Walsh; and clippings (Box-folder 66: 8)
  - "Law, Morals, and the Spirit,", 1956 April 3 (Box-folder 66: 9)
    Speech, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana. Outline and correspondence with Ralph Slovenko
  - "On Toynbee's Study of History,", 1956 June 14 (Box-folder 66: 10)
    Speech, Conference on Democratic Theory, Buck Hill Falls, Pennsylvania. Correspondence with William S. Stokes
  - "Dynamics of Institutions,", 1956 November (Box-folder 66: 11)
    Speech, Foreign Service Institute, Washington, D.C. Notes and correspondence with Robert Rossow, Jr.
  - "Zusammenbruch der Ideologie in unserer Zeit,", 1956 December (Box-folder 66: 12)
    Speech, University of Frankfurt, West Germany. Outline, correspondence with Max Horkheimer, and clipping
  - Order and History, Vol.II: The World of the Polis, 1957
    - Typescript (Box-folder 67: 1-3)
    - Reviews
      Includes correspondence
      - General
        See Order and History, Vol.III